在开始学习这门课程前,我要给你们快速讲一下
Before we start with the technical
material, I wanna give you a quick
密码学的简要概述，以及密码学的不同领域。
overview of what cryptography is about and
the different areas of cryptography. So
密码学的核心当然是安全通信，他本质上
the core of cryptography of course is
secure communication that essentially
由两部分组成。第一部分是安全秘钥的建立，然后是
consists of two parts. The first is
secured key establishment and then how do
利用共享秘钥进行安全通信。我们说过
we communicate securely once we have a
shared key. We already said that secured
安全秘钥的建立是指Alice和Bob互相通信
key establishment essentially amounts to
Alice and Bob sending messages to one
这样在协议的最后，双方达成共享秘钥k
another such that at the end of this
protocol, there's a shared key that they
除了共享秘钥，事实上
both agree on, shared key K, and beyond
that, beyond just a shared key, in fact
Alice应该知道她在和Bob通信同样Bob应该知道他在和Alice通信
Alice would know that she's talking to Bob
and Bob would know that he's talking to
但是弱的攻击者监听该对话却无法得知
Alice. But a poor attacker who listens in
on this conversation has no idea what the
共享秘钥，本讲稍后我们来看怎样操作。现在
shared key is. And we'll see how to do
that later on in the course. Now once they
他们一旦达成共享秘钥，他们希望使用该秘钥安全地交换信息
have a shared key, they want exchange
messages securely using this key, and
我们将会讨论满足他们的加密机制，这样就使得
we'll talk about encryption schemes that
allow them to do that in such a way that
攻击者无法知道什么消息在被传来传去。
an attacker can't figure out what messages
are being sent back and forth. And
进一步说，攻击者甚至无法篡改通信内容，一旦篡改，立刻被检测到
furthermore an attacker cannot even tamper
with this traffic without being detected.
换句话说，加密机制提供了机密性和
In other words, these encryption schemes
provide both confidentiality and
完整性。不过密码学的功能远不止这两点。
integrity. But cryptography does much,
much, much more than just these two
我来给你举一些例子。第一个例子
things. And I want to give you a few
examples of that. So the first example I
叫做数字签名。数字签名
want to give you is what's called a
digital signature. So a digital signature,
基本上与实际手写签名类似，在实际中
basically, is the analog of the signature
in the physical world. In the physical
当你签署一份文件时，你在文件上写下你签名
world, remember when you sign a document,
essentially, you write your signature on
你的签名总是一样的。你总是在所有的文件上
that document and your signature is always
the same. You always write the same
签同样的字，在数字世界中，
signature on all documents that you wanna
sign. In the digital world, this can't
签名不能这样因为一旦攻击者获得我的一个文件签名
possibly work because if the attacker just
obtained one signed document from me, he
他可以复制粘贴到别的我不想
can cut and paste my signature unto some
other document that I might not have
签字的文件上。所以在数字世界中，
wanted to sign. And so, it's simply not
possible in a digital world that my
我的签名对我想签的所有不同文件不可能一样。本门课的
signature is the same for all documents
that I want to sign. So we're gonna talk
后半部分我们将讨论如何构建数字签名
about how to construct digital signatures
in the second half of the course. It's
这是一个很有趣的部件，我们将确切地看到如何去做。
really quite an interesting primitive and
we'll see exactly how to do it. Just to
提示你一下，数字签名基本上就是
give you a hint, the way digital
signatures work is basically by making the
待签内容的一个函数值，因此，一个攻击者
digital signature via function of the
content being signed. So an attacker who
想要复制我的签名到其他文件上将无法成功
tries to copy my signature from one
document to another is not gonna succeed
因为，数字签名，新文件与旧文件的函数值不一致
because the signature. On the new document
is not gonna be the proper function of the
所以签名验证失败，就像我说过的
data in the new document, and as a result,
the signature won't verify. And as I said,
稍后我们将确切地看到如何构建数字签名构造
we're gonna see exactly how to construct
digital signatures later on and then we'll
并且我们会证明这些构造是安全的。我想说的密码学的
prove that those constructions are secure.
Another application of cryptography that I
另一个应用是匿名通信，想象一下
wanted to mention, is anonymous
communication. So, here, imagine user
用户Alice想和某个聊天服务器Bob说话，也许她想谈论病情
Alice wants to talk to some chat server,
Bob. And, perhaps she wants to talk about
所以她想匿名，从而聊天服务器
a medical condition, and so she wants to
do that anonymously, so that the chat
并不知道她是谁。有一个标准方法叫
server doesn't actually know who she is.
Well, there's a standard method, called a
mixnet，可以允许Alice通过公共互联网与Bob通信
mixnet, that allows Alice to communicate
over the public internet with Bob through
经过经过一系列代理，最终让Bob无从得知对方身份
a sequence of proxies such that at the end
of the communication Bob has no idea who he
mixnet的工作原理基本上是，当Alice给Bob发出信息
just talked to. The way mixnets work
is basically as Alice sends her messages
经过一系列代理时，信息被适当地加密 解密
to Bob through a sequence of proxies,
these messages get encrypted and
以至于Bob不知道通信对方身份而且代理们
decrypted appropriately so that Bob has no
idea who he talked to and the proxies
也不知道Alice在和Bob通信，或者压根不知道
themselves don't even know that Alice is
talking to Bob, or that actually who is
谁在和谁通信。匿名通信的一个有趣事实是
talking to whom more generally. One
interesting thing about this anonymous
它是双向的，换句话说
communication channel is, this is
bi-directional. In other words, even
尽管Bob不知道他在跟谁说话，他依然可以回应Alice
though Bob has no idea who he's talking
to, he can still respond to Alice and
Alice可以收到回复。一旦我们有了匿名通信
Alice will get those messages. Once we
have anonymous communication, we can build
我们可以建立其他隐私机制。我想为大家举个叫匿名
other privacy mechanisms. And I wanna give
you one example which is called anonymous
数字现金的例子。记得在现实中如果我有一美元
digital cash. Remember that in the
physical world if I have a physical
我可以去书店买本书，书店老板并不知道我是谁
dollar, I can walk into a bookstore and
buy a book and the merchant would have no
问题是我们能不能做同样的事情在数字世界里
idea who I am. The question is whether we
can do the exact same thing in the digital
在数字世界里，Alice可以有一个数字美元
world. In the digital world, basically,
Alice might have a digital dollar,
一个数字美元硬币。她可能想在网上购物花掉这一美元
a digital dollar coin. And she might wanna
spend that digital dollar at some online
比如网上书店之类。现在我们要让Alice
merchants, perhaps some online bookstore.
Now, what we'd like to do is make it so
在书店花掉这块硬币，而书店不知道
that when Alice spends her coin at the
bookstore, the bookstore would have no
Alice是谁。这样我们提供了与现实一样的匿名
idea who Alice is. So we provide the same
anonymity that we get from physical cash.
问题是在数字世界里，Alice使用的硬币
Now the problem is that in the digital
world, Alice can take the coin that she
她可以在花掉之前复制该硬币
had, this one dollar coin, and before she spent
it, she can actually make copies of it.
突然间姐不是一美元硬币了
And then all of a sudden instead of just
having just one dollar coin now all
她突然间就有了三美元硬币，它们当然是一样的
of a sudden she has three dollar coins and
they're all the same of course, and
没什么能阻止她复制硬币并花掉它。
there's nothing preventing her from taking
those replicas of a dollar coin and
那问题就是，我们该如何提供匿名数字现金
spending it at other merchants. And so the
question is how do we provide anonymous
同时还要防止Alice重复花费
digital cash? But at the same time, also
prevent Alice from double spending the
购买不同的商品。在某些情况下这里有矛盾
dollar coin at different merchants. In
some sense there's a paradox here where
安全和匿名是相悖的，因为我们有匿名现金
anonymity is in conflict with security
because if we have anonymous cash there's
将没有什么能阻止Alice重复花费
nothing to prevent Alice from double
spending the coin and because the coin is
因为硬币是匿名的，我们无法找到诈骗者。
anonymous we have no way of telling who
committed this fraud. And so the question
那我们如何解决该问题呢？事实上，这是完全可行的
is how do we resolve this tension. And it
turns out, it's completely doable. And
我们将会讨论到匿名数字现金。给大家点提示
we'll talk about anonymous digital cash
later on. Just to give you a hint, I'll
我们的方法是确保当Alice只花费一次时
say that the way we do it is basically by
making sure that if Alice spends the coin
没人知道她是谁。但如果她花费多于一次
once then no one knows who she is, but if
she spends the coin more than once, all of
她的个人信息将会突然全部暴露
a sudden, her identity is completely
exposed and then she could be subject to
她将面临各种法律问题。那就是匿名现金
all sorts of legal problems. And so that's
how anonymous digital cash would
从高层次来说如何工作的。本课稍后将介绍如何实现它
work at a high level and we'll see how to
implement it later on in the course.
密码学的另一应用是关于更多抽象的协议
Another application of cryptography has to
do with more abstract protocols, but
不过在我说一般结果之前，我想给大家看两个例子
before I speak the general result, I
want to give you two examples. So the
第一个例子与选举系统有关。这有个选举的问题
first example has to do with election
systems. So here's the election problem.
假设有两个党派，0和1，供选民投票
Suppose ... we have two parties, party zero
and party one. And voters vote for these
比如说，这个选民投给了0，那个投给了1，等等
parties. So for example, this voter could
have voted for party zero, this voter voted for
在本次选举中，0得三票，1得二票
party one. And so on. So in this election,
party zero got three votes and party two
0当然是本次选举的获胜者
got two votes. So the winner of the
election, of course, is party zero. But
但是更一般的，胜者是获得多数票的一方
more generally, the winner of the election
is the party who receives the majority of
现在，投票的问题如下，投票者
the votes. Now, the voting problem is the
following. The voters would somehow like
可能会计算多数投票结果，不过却不知道每个人的投票结果
to compute the majority of the votes, but
do it in such a way such that nothing else
明白了吗？那么问题来了，要怎么实现它?
is revealed about their individual votes.
Okay? So the question is how to do that?
为此我们引入了一个选举中心
And to do so, we're gonna introduce an
election center who's gonna help us
用来帮我们计算大多数票，但投票结果保密
compute the majority, but keep the votes
otherwise secret. And what the parties
各派将把他们的投票加密后送给选举中心
will do is they will each send the funny
encryption of their votes to the election
投票结束时，选举中心可以计算出胜者
center in such a way that at the end of
the election, the election center is able
但除了选举胜者之外
to compute and output the winner of the
election. However, other than the winner
各个投票结果无从知晓
of the election, nothing else is revealed
about the individual votes. The individual
个人投票是完全私密的当然，选举中心还要验证
votes otherwise remain completely private.
Of course the election center is also
投票者是否能投票以及只能投一次
gonna verify that this voter for example
is allowed to vote and that the voter has
除了那些信息，选举中心及其他人
only voted once. But other than that
information the election center and the
无从知晓各投票人的选择
rest of the world learned nothing else
about that voter's vote other than the
除了最终选举结果。所以这是一个涉及六方协议的例子
result of the election. So this is an
example of a protocol that involves six
在这个情况下，有五个投票者在一个选举中心
parties. In this case, there are five
voters in one election center. These
参与者计算他们自己的投票结果，最后选举的结果可以得出
parties compute amongst themselves. And at
the end of the computation, the result of
不过个人投票决定是不被泄露的。
the election is known but nothing else is
revealed about the individual inputs. Now
对于私密的拍卖也有类似问题
a similar problem comes up in the context
of private auctions. So in a private
在私密拍卖中每个买家都有自己愿意出的标价
auction every bidder has his own bid that
he wants to bid. And now suppose the
假设拍卖机制使用的是Vickrey拍卖
auction mechanism that's being used is
what's called a Vickrey auction where the
Vickrey拍卖的中标者为出价最高者
definition of a Vickrey auction is that
the winner is the highest bidder. But the
但中标者付的钱为第二高的出价
amounts that the winner pays is actually
the second highest bid. So he pays the
所以他付第二高的出价，这就是Vickrey拍卖机制
second highest bid. Okay, so this is a
standard auction mechanism called the
现在我们想做的是让参与者能计算
Vickrey auction. And now what we'd like to
do is basically enable the participants to
算出最高出价者和该付的钱
compute, to figure out who the highest
bidder is and how much he's supposed to
但除了这些，所有其他关于个人投票的信息保密
pay, but other than that, all other
information about the individual bids
例如，最高出价者的数额保密
should remain secret. So for example, the
actual amount that the highest bidder bid
为公众所知的只有第二高价的数额
should remain secret. The only thing that
should become public is the second highest
和出最高价者是谁。又一次的，我们现在需要
bid and the identity of the highest
bidder. So again now, the way we will do
引入拍卖中心，类似的选举中心，
that is we'll introduce an auction center, and
in a similar way, essentially, everybody
每个人都会把其加密的投标送给拍卖中心
will send their encrypted bids to the
auction center. The auction center will
拍卖中心会计算中标者是谁，以及第二高价
compute the identity of the winner and in
fact he will also compute the second
不过除了这些，个人标价不被泄露
highest bid but other than these two
values, nothing else is revealed about the
这其实是一个更广泛的问题
individual bids. Now, this is actually an
example of a much more general problem
叫做安全多方计算。让我解释一下安全多方计算是什么
called secure multi-party computation. Let
me explain what secure multi-party
抽象的，参与者自己有一个秘密输入
computation is about. So here, basically
abstractly, the participants have a secret
在选举中，输入将是投票
inputs to themselves. So, in the case of
an election, the inputs would be the
在拍卖中，输入将是秘密投标
votes. In the case of an auction, the
inputs would be the secret bids. And then
然后他们想计算一个关于这些输入的函数
what they would like to do is compute some
sort of a function of their inputs.
在选举中，函数为大多数
Again, in the case of an election, the
function's a majority. In the case of
在拍卖中，函数为第二高价X1到X4的最大值
auction, the function happens to be the
second highest, largest number among x one
问题是，怎么办才能得知函数值
to x four. And the question is, how can
they do that, such that the value of the
同时个人投票信息保密呢？
function is revealed, but nothing else is
revealed about the individual votes? So
我来展示一个蠢且不安全的方法。我们引入一个可信赖方
let me show you kind of a dumb, insecure
way of doing it. What we do is introduce a
这个可信赖方收集个人输入
trusted party. And then, this trusted
authority basically collects individual
它保证不泄露个人输入
inputs. And it kinda promises to keep the
individual inputs secret, so that only it
它自己是知道的。
然后，可信赖方公开发布函数结果
would know what they are. And then, it
publishes the value of the function, to
目的是，函数值公开
the world. So, the idea is now that the
value of the function became public, but
但个人输入依然未泄露
nothing else is revealed about the
individual inputs. But, of course, you got
当然，你是信任这个可信赖方的，若出于某些原因，
this trusted authority that you got to
trust, and if for some reason it's not
它不可信了，你就有麻烦了，密码学有一个非常核心的定理
trustworthy, then you have a problem. And
so, there's a very central theorem in
揭示了一个非常惊人的事实。定理说
crypto and it really is quite a
surprising fact. That says that any
任何你想做的计算，任何函数F
computation you'd like to do, any function
F you'd like to compute, that you can
只要你能用可信任方计算，一定也可以不借助可信任方完成
compute with a trusted authority, you can
also do without a trusted authority.
让我从上层来解释下，基本上，我们想做的
Let me at a high level explain what this
means. Basically, what we're gonna do, is
就是去掉可信任方。这样各方不会把他们的输入
we're gonna get rid of the authority. So
the parties are actually not gonna send
给可信任方。事实上系统中没有可信任方了
their inputs to the authority. And, in
fact, there's no longer going to be an
取而代之的是，各参与者使用
authority in the system. Instead, what the
parties are gonna do, is they're gonna
某些协议互相通信。在协议的最后
talk to one another using some protocol.
Such that at the end of the protocol all
函数值突然被大家知道
of a sudden the value of the function
becomes known to everybody. And yet
除此之外无任何信息泄露，换句话说，
nothing other than the value of the
function is revealed. In other words, the
个人投票依然保密。没有可信任方
individual inputs is still kept secret.
But again there's no authority, there's
各方相互交流就可以算出最终结果
just a way for them to talk to one another
such that the final output is revealed. So
这是一个很一般的结论。其普适性有点惊人
this is a fairly general result, it's kind
of a surprising fact that is at all
事实上，在本课的最后，我们将看到
doable. And in fact it is and towards the
end of the class we'll actually see how to
这将如何实现。密码学还有些应用
make this happen. Now, there are some
applications of cryptography that I can't
我无法分类，只能说他们很神奇
classify any other way other than to say
that they are purely magical. Let me give
我给两个例子。第一个叫私有外包计算
you two examples of that. So the first is
what's called privately outsourcing
为了阐明这一点，我会举一个谷歌搜索的例子
computation. So I'll give you an example
of a Google search just to illustrate the
假设Alice有一个搜索请求
point. So imagine Alice has a search query
that she wants to issue. It turns out that
事实上有很特殊的加密机制，可以
there are very special encryption schemes
such that Alice can send an encryption of
把Alice的请求加密后交给谷歌。由于加密机制的特性
her query to Google. And then because of
the property of the encryption scheme
谷歌可以在加密后的值上运算，无需知道原文是什么
Google can actually compute on the
encrypted values without knowing what the
所以谷歌可以在加密的请求上，运行庞大的搜索算法
plain texts are. So Google can actually
run its massive search algorithm on the
得到的是加密的结果。好，谷歌将加密后的结果
encrypted query and recover in encrypted
results. Okay. Google will send the
返回给Alice。她解密后就会得到搜索结果了
encrypted results back to Alice. Alice
will decrypt and then she will receive the
神奇的地方在于谷歌只能看到请求的加密形式，别无他物
results. But the magic here is all Google
saw was just encryptions of her queries
所以谷歌不知道Alice刚才搜索什么
and nothing else. And so, Google as a
result has no idea what Alice just
尽管Alice知道了她想要的东西
searched for and nevertheless Alice
actually learned exactly what she
好，这些是加密机制里很神奇的内容
wanted to learn. Okay so, these are
magical kind of encryption schemes. They're
他们相对较新，只有两三年的发展历史
fairly recent, this is only a new
development from about two or three years
允许加密数据上的计算，尽管我们不知道加密的内容
ago, that allows us to compute on encrypted
data, even though we don't really know
在大家急着去想怎么实现这个之前
what's inside the encryption. Now, before
you rush off and think about implementing
我应当警告大家目前这只是理论结果
this, I should warn you that this is
really at this point just theoretical, in
也就是说基于加密数据的谷歌搜索
the sense that running a Google search on
encryption data probably would take a
很可能会花上亿年，不过这个可行的事实可能已经很惊人了
billion years. But nevertheless, just the
fact that this is doable is already really
对于相对简单的计算也已经有应用了。
surprising, and is already quite useful
for relatively simple computations. So in
事实上我们稍后会看到这个的一些应用。另一个神奇的应用
fact, we'll see some applications of this
later on. The other magical application I
我将展示的叫做零知识。特别的，我要
want to show you is what's called zero
knowledge. And in particular, I'll tell
告诉大家有关知识的零知识的证明。
you about something called the zero
knowledge proof of knowledge. So here ...
Alice知道一个特定的数N
what happens is there's a certain
number N, which Alice knows. And the way
数N为两个大素数的积
the number N was constructed is as a
product of two large primes. So, imagine
假设我们有两个素数P和Q，每个认为有1000位
here we have two primes, P and Q. Each one
you can think of it as like 1000 digits.
你很可能知道乘两个1000位的数容易计算
And you probably know that multiplying
two 1000-digit numbers is fairly easy. But if
但如果给定乘积，求素数分解
I just give you their product, figuring
out their factorization into primes is
将非常困难。事实上，我们将利用这一事实
actually quite difficult. And, in fact,
we're gonna use the fact that factoring is
用因子分解的困难性建立公钥密码系统，将在本课后半段介绍。
difficult to build public key cryptosystems
in the second half of the course.
好，那么Alice有大整数N，她知道N的因子分解
Okay, so Alice happens to have this number
N, and she also knows the factorization of
Bob只知道数N，他不知道N的因子分解
N. Now Bob just has the number N. He
doesn't actually know the factorization.
知识的零知识证明的神奇之处在于
Now, the magical fact about the zero
knowledge proof of knowledge, is that
Alice能向Bob证明她知道N的因子分解
Alice can prove to Bob that she knows the
factorization of N. Yes, you can actually
是的，你可以把这个证明给Bob，Bob检查后确信Alice
give this proof to Bob, that Bob can
check, and become convinced that Alice
知道如何分解但是，Bob不知道因子P和Q
knows the factorization of N, however Bob
learns nothing at all. About the factors P
这是可证明的。Bob完全不知道P和Q两个因子
and Q, and this is provable. Bob
absolutely learns nothing at all about the
这个论断实际上很广泛
factors P and Q. And the statement
actually is very, very general. This is
它不仅仅是证明N的因子分解，事实上有很多谜题
not just about proving the factorization
of N. In fact, almost any puzzle that you
你希望证明你知道答案，你可以证明它是你的知识
want to prove that you know an answer to,
you can prove it is your knowledge. So if
如果你解决了一个填字游戏，可能填字游戏不是最好的例子
you have a crossword puzzle that you've
solved. Well, maybe crosswords is not the
如果你有一个数独谜题，例如
best example. But if you have like a
Sudoku puzzle, for example, that you want
你想证明你已经解决了，你可以向Bob证明
to prove that you've solved, you can prove
it to Bob in a way that Bob would learn
Bob无法知道怎么解的，不过Bob会相信你对本题有解。
nothing at all about the solution, and yet
Bob would be convinced that you really do
好，那些是很神奇的应用。
have a solution to this puzzle. Okay. So
those are kind of magical applications.
最后我想说的是现代密码学
And so the last thing I want to say is
that modern cryptography is a very
是很严格的科学。事实上我们描述的每一个概念
rigorous science. And in fact, every
concept we're gonna describe is gonna
都依照非常严格的三步，我们将反复利用到这三步
follow three very rigorous steps, okay,
and we're gonna see these three steps
我想解释一下他们是什么。第一件
again and again and again so I wanna
explain what they are. So the first thing
是当我们引入新的部件时，例如数字签名
we're gonna do when we introduce a new
primitive like a digital signature is
我们要准确描述威胁模型是什么
we're gonna specify precisely what the
threat model is. That is, what can an
就是说攻击者如何攻击数字签名，伪造签名的目的何在？
attacker do to attack a digital signature
and what is his goal in forging
好，我们将严格定义签名的含义
signatures? Okay, so we're gonna define
exactly what does it mean for a signature
例如，用于不可伪造。不可伪造。好
for example to be unforgeable.
Unforgeable. Okay and I'm giving digital
我拿数字签名作为一个例子，对每个我们描述的部件
signatures just as an example. For every
primitive we describe we're gonna
准确定义威胁模型，然后我们要提出构架
precisely define what the threat model is.
Then we're gonna propose a construction
证明任何攻击者在这个威胁模型下
and then we're gonna give a proof that any
attacker that's able to attack the
可以攻击这个构架，那么这个攻击者也可以用这种方法
construction under this threat model. That
attacker can also be used to solve some
解决根本性难题。如果问题真的很难
underlying hard problem. And as a result,
if the problem really is hard, that
实际上就证明了攻击者无法在威胁模型下，破解这个构架。
actually proves that no attacker can break
the construction under the threat model.
不过这三步非常重要
Okay. But these three steps are actually
quite important. In the case of
对于签名，我们会定义签名可伪造的含义
signatures, we'll define what it means for
a signature to be, forgeable, then we'll
然后我们给一个构架，例如我们会说任何人若能破解我们
give a construction, and then for example
we'll say that anyone who can break our
的构架，他也可以用他破解的方法来解决因子分解问题
construction can then be used to say
factor integers, which is believed to be a
后者是公认的难题。好的，我们将通篇遵循这三步
hard problem. Okay, so we're going to
follow these three steps throughout, and
大家将看到这个实际上是如何发生的。好，本节结束
then you'll see how this actually comes
about. Okay, so this is the end of the
下一节我们要简要谈一下密码学
segment. And then in the next segment
we'll talk a little bit about the history
的历史。
of cryptography.